A Guide to the Albert J. Wasserman papers, 1925-2003
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Albert J. Wasserman papers 1925-2003
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
2012/Jun/11
5 linear feet.
Wasserman, Albert J.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open to research; however some files with confidential information are restricted. Redacted copies may be made available at the discretion of the Special Collections and Archives staff.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Gail Wasserman Hart, 2011.
Biographical Information
Albert Julian Wasserman was born in Richmond, Virginia to Ann and Stanley Wasserman on January 23, 1928. Wasserman attended Thomas Jefferson High School and then the University of Virginia where he was a member of the Phi Beta Kappa Honor Society. He began medical school at the Medical College of Virginia (MCV) in 1948. Wasserman was a member of Alpha Omega Alpha Medical Honor Society, Sigma Zeta National Honorary Scientific Socieyt, and Phi Delta Epsilon. He graduated in 1951 and was appointed to Beth Hospital in Massachusetts. He received additional training at MCV before entering the Air Force.
Wasserman returned to MCV in 1956 and remained for the rest of his career. He was a professor of medicine and clinical pharmacology, served as associate dean of curriculum, and as executive associate dean. During his tenure he was chosen as "Teacher of the Year" in 1977-1979, received the Special Award for Contributions to Education for the MCV Classes of 1981-1984, and given the Dean's Award for outstanding contribution to students and faculty at MCV in 1990.Wasserman served as editor or reviewer for several professional publication and was author or co-aurthor of more than 100 scientific articles. In addition to his work at MCV, Wasserman served as the Chief of Medical Service at the VA Hospital, Richmond from 1960-1963. He was also involved in numerous academic and professional organizations and was elected a Fellow of the American College of Physicians. In 1992 he was awarded the MCV Alumni Association Distinguished Faculty Award. That same year Wasserman retired from MCV and was granted Professor Emeritus status. He also establish an endowed pharmacology award in his name. The Albert J. Wasserman, M.D. Student Award in Pharmacology is given each year to the M2 student with the highest score in that course. Wasserman was also active in the local community. He served as PResident of Beth Sholom Home and of Temple Beth-El.
Wasserman married his high school sweetheart Martele "Marty" Sporn on June 27, 1948 while he was in medical school. Mrs. Wasserman, a graduate of Richmond Professional Institute, later became the secretary to Dr. William T. Sanger, President of of MCV. They had three children. Dr. Wasserman died on September 6, 2006 in Richmond, Virginia.
Scope and Content
The papers of Albert J. Wasserman include materials relating to his career at the Medical College of Virginia (MCV) as a professor of medicine and clinical pharmacology. These materials including his subject files and his person papers.
Series 1: Subject Files, 1925-1995. This series consists of a representative sample of materials from Wasserman's subject files which include lecture notes, abstracts, journal articles, grand rounds case studies, and other materials related to medical issues that Dr. Wasserman studied and researched.
Series 2: Personal Papers, 1957-2003. This series includes personal correspondence; materials relating to Wasserman's employment such as his letter of appointment to the faculty, personnel forms, employee handbook, and related materials; items related to his retirement including cards, letters, invitations, and his personal remarks from his retirement reception; MCV related programs; the endowment agreement for the creation of the Wasserman Student Award in Pharmacology; ephemera, including his MCV ID; and other related items.
Arrangement
This collection is divided into two series:
Series 1, Subject Files, 1925-1995.
Series 2, Personal Papers, 1957-2003.
Efforts have been made to maintain the original file titles and organization. Both series are arranged alphabetically and the material with the files are arranged chronologically where applicable.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Material
This collection also included several artifacts a hemometer and hemacytomer, a head mirror reflector, and a glass decanter with the VCU seal.These items have been added to the medical artifacts. The collection also included papers and materials from Albert Wasserman's wife, Matele Sporn Wasserman. These materials have been transferred to Cabell Special Collection.
Index Terms
Persons:
Wasserman, Albert J., 1928-2006
Corporate Names:
Medical College of Virginia; Virginia Commonwealth University
Subjects:
Pharmacology; Medicine
Contents List
- Subject Files 1925-1995 (Box 1-4)
  - Allopurinol Hypersensitivity Syndrome, 1976 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Analgesics 1973-1990 (Box-folder 1:2-3)
    Access restrictions: Some materials restricted.
  - Anti-arrhythimic Drugs - Lecture, 1976-1991 (Box-folder 1:4-5)
  - Anticoagulants in Acute Myocardial Infarction, 1965-1969 (Box-folder 1:6)
    Contains manuscript, tables, and lecture notes.
  - Asthma, 1981-1991 (Box-folder 1:7)
    Contains notes on bronchiodialator lecture, slides.
  - Autonomic Pharmacology, 1959-1973 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Atherosclerosis - Lipids, 1964-1976 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Boston Collaborative Drug Surveillance Program, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Calcium Channel Blockers, 1981-1987 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Cardiac Cycle, Events of, 1964-1971 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Cerebral Blood Flow, 1948-1972 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Cerebral Blood Flow and Ammonia, 1960-1966 (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Cerebral Blood Flow and Hypoxemia, Reference, 1957-1970 (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Cerebral Blood Flow and Oxygen Data, 1965 (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Colestipol study, 1970-1977 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Congestive Heart Failure, Lecture, 1976-1985 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Common Cold, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 1:19)
  - Chronic Obstructive pulmonary Disease, Drug Rx, 1982-1991 (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Coronary Distress, Rx After Myocardial Infarction, 1979-1989 (Box-folder 2:1)
    Contains lecture notes, abstracts, and articles.
  - Cromolyn Sodium, 1971-1975 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Drug Interactions, 1976-1986 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Digitalis - Lecture, 1984-1991 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Digitalis - Notes, 1955-1971 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Digoxin, Overdoese, 1970-1982 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Digoxin - Toxicity, 1967-1976 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Drugs - Costs, Generics, Equivalency, 1974-1991 (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Drugs - Development, 1974-1990 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Drugs - Evaluation Lecture, 1982-1992 (Box-folder 2:10)
    Contains lecture notes, abstracts, articles, and some literature from medical conferences.
  - Drugs - Laws, 1970-1981 (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Drugs - Virginia Voluntary Formulary Act, 1979-1984 (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Familial Hyperlipemia, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 2:13)
    Access Restrictions: This file is restricted.
  - Foundations in Clinical Medicine - Geriatrics, 1995 (Box-folder 2:14)
  - Genetics and Lipid Metabolism, 1971-1976 (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Geriactrics, 1971-1986 (Box-folder 2:16)
  - Geriatric Pharmacology, 1982-1988 (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Hemochromatosis, 1933-1964 (Box-folder 2:18)
    Access Restrictions: Some materials are restricted.
    Contains correspondence, article reprints, notes, and images.
  - History of Medical Education, 1925-1991 (Box-folder 2:19)
  - Hyperlipidemia - Clinic Lecture, 1992 (Box-folder 2:20)
  - Hyperlipidemia - Treatment, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 2:21)
  - Hyperlipoproteinemia, 1967-1991 (Box-folder 2:22)
    Contains reprint of Holimon and Wasserman article, "Autopsy Findings in Type 3 Herperlipoproteinemia," study notes, articles and abstracts.
  - Hyperlipoproteinemia - Lovastatin, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 2:23)
  - Hyperlipoproteinemia - Diagnosis and Treatment (Box-folder 2:24)
    Contains lecture notes and handouts, articles, and abstracts.
  - Hypertension, 1972-1988 (Box-folder 3:1)
    General file includes notes, abstracts, and related materials.
  - Hypertension - Calcium Channel Blockers, 1982-1987 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Hypertension - Crises, Diagnosis, & Prescription, 1974-1989 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Hypertension - Current Therapy, 1985-1991 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Hypertension - Diet, 1971-1987 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Hypertension - Drugs vs Renin Angiotensin, 1979-1985 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Hypertension - Elderly, 1979-1987 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Hypertension - New Drugs, 1978-1980 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Hypertension - Pharmacology Lecture, 1984-1988 (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Hypertension - Pathogenesis & Renin Profiles, 1977-1985 (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Hypertension Panel - M-IV Update Course, 1992 (Box-folder 3:11)
  - Lipid Cases, 1987 (Box-folder 3:12)
  - Lipid Lecture & Notes, 1986-1990 (Box-folder 3:13)
  - Lipid Treatment, 1990 (Box-folder 3:14)
  - Mucolytics - Cough Drugs, 1971-1980 (Box-folder 3:15)
  - Mucormycosis, 1961-1979 (Box-folder 3:16)
    Contains notes, abstracts, and reprints of the 1961 article "Cerebral Mucormycosis," by Wasserman, Shields, and Sporn.
  - Muscle Blood Flow, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 3:17)
    Contains notes, abstracts, and reprints of the 1975 article "Blood flow in muscle groups and drug absorption," by Evans, Proctor, Fratkind, Velandia, and Wasserman.
  - Myocardial infarction - Prognosis, 1968-1992 (Box-folder 3:18)
  - Myocardial Infarction - Rx, 1967-1991 (Box-folder 3:19)
  - Nitrates - Lecture, 1982-1987 (Box-folder 3:20)
  - Nutritional & Diet Information, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 3:21)
  - Osteoporosis, 1998 (Box-folder 3:22)
  - Presentation - UVA, 1968 (Box-folder 3:23)
    Contains notes and presentation text titled "The Management of a Patient's Lifetime of Cirulatory Disease."
  - Pharmacy Student Physician Visitations, 1978-1982 (Box-folder 3:24)
  - Pharmacy Student Physician Visitation - Evaluations, no date (Box-folder 3:25)
  - Pharmacotherapeutic Conference, 1973-1981 (Box-folder 3:26)
  - Primary Pulmonary Hypertension, 1961-1984 (Box-folder 3:27)
  - Psychopharmacology, 1994 (Box-folder 3:28)
  - Raynaud's Phenomenon, 1963-1990 (Box-folder 4:1)
    Contains notes, grand rounds cases, images, articles, and reprints of the 1969 article "Effect of Reserpine in Raynaud's Phenomenon," by Kontos and Wasserman.
  - Renin - Angiotensin, 1968-1977 (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Reprints, 1957-1984 (Box-folder 4:3)
    This file contains reprints of articles that Wasserman authored or co-authored.
  - Risk Factors - Lecture, 1978-1987 (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Sexually Transmitted Diseases, 1949-1991 (Box-folder 4:5)
    This file contains abstracts, notes, pamphlets and booklets on sexually transmitted diseases. Included is a 1949 handbook titled "Diagnosis and Treatmenf of Syphilis," and information on the 1975 amendment to the Virginia Marriage Examination Law, including pamphlets and the blue examination cards.
  - Sotalol, 1982-1987 (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Takayasu Syndrome, 1962-1967 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Theophyllines/Bronchodilators, 1975-1981 (Box-folder 4:8)
  - Vasculitis, 1997 (Box-folder 4:9)
  - Wolff-Parkinson-White Syndrome, 1967-1989 (Box-folder 4:10)
  - Xanthomatous Disorders, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 4:11)
- Personal Papers 1957-2003 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, undated, 1957, 1988-1992, 2003 (Box-folder 4:12)
    This file contains personal correspondence and is mainly comprised of notes send on the occasion of Wasserman receiving the MCV Alumni Distinguished Faculty Award and a few letters from family members.
  - Endowment Fund of the Jewish Community Federation of Richmond, 2002 (Box-folder 4:13)
  - Ephemera (Box-folder 4:14)
    This folder contains a photograph of the Wassermans, his id badge from MCV, and two patched from Thomas Jefferson High School which Wasserman attended.
  - MCV Employment and Faculty records, 1957-1990 (Box-folder 4:15)
    This file contains information relating to Wasserman's empoyment at MCV including an undated employee handbook (prior to 1968).
  - MCV - Programs, 1986-1987, 1992 (Box-folder 4:16)
    Contains MCV graduation programs from 1986 and 1987, Medical Division Reunion programs, and Service Award Programs.
  - MCV - Retirement, 1986-1987, 1992 (Box-folder 4:17)
    Contains letters, cards, notes, invitations, and other items related to Wasserman's retirement from MCV in 1992.
  - Wasserman Student Award in Pharmacology, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 4:18)
    Contains the endowment agreement for the creation of the award, correspondence, and a program from the 1993 Medical Students Honor Day where the award was first given.